Coping With Misfortune
Hello,
It's great to meet you.
(Audience Applause)
As we go through life,
tragedies like the Sewol ferry
incident strike us unexpectedly.
As many were affected by the incident,
a lot of people came together
to console each other.
But when tragedy strikes an individual,
people don't always acknowledge it.
Then you feel like the sky is falling and
the earth is crumbling beneath your feet.
We use the expression that you
'lose your mind'.
Nobody wants to experience
such misfortunes.
And we pray to God or Buddha to prevent
misfortunes from happening to us.
And yet in life misfortunes
do happen to us.
It would be nice if they didn't,
but they do happen in reality.
If we have no choice
but to be unhappy with such misfortunes,
we could never reach Nirvana, the state of
true happiness that Buddha mentioned.
The goal of practice is to become
the master of our lives
and maintain happiness even when
unwanted misfortunes happen to us.
If the goal to having a religion is
to prevent misfortunes from striking us,
and to have a nice afterlife,
the goal of practicing is
to reach a state where we don't get
startled in the face of misfortunes,
to a point that
we're not even afraid of death.
The goal of practice is
Enlightenment and Nirvana.
It is to become
a person that feels no pain,
and to not be bound to any conditions.
It is to become a free person.
No matter who you are -
whether you are a man or women, adult or
child, Korean or Japanese, back or white,
healthy or physically challenged,
born into wealth or poverty,
whether you had a difficult childhood,
whether you became an orphan,
whether you are a victim of sexual abuse,
whether you were raised by strangers,
whether you are divorced,
no matter
what you've experienced in the past,
everyone can be happy.
Everyone deserves to be happy.
Do you agree?
Everyone can be happy.
Everyone has the potential
to become a Buddha.
Everyone can become a Buddha.
Everyone is a Buddha.
Even though we have the right
to be happy and can be happy,
we are not happy in real life.
We are all Buddhas, and yet we live
the life of unenlightened beings.
So how can we recover
our nature as Buddha?
How can we live happily?
To say "He practiced so hard that he
survived through a near-death situation"
is not a compliment for a practitioner.
"Others would have acted as
if it's a near-death situation,
and yet he remained his calm"
This would be the best compliment.
That should be your goal.
You all can become like this.
Don't hold on to the past. Don't speak of
the promises your spouse hasn't kept.
If you do, you will be miserable
until the day you die.
What happened in the past
is not important.
What's important is
what you'll do going forward.
Do humans change their minds?
Or do they never change their minds
once their minds are made up?
(Audience) They change.
People change their minds.
And yet we insist people shouldn't change.
It's natural for people
to change their minds.
You should accept the fact
that people change,
then decide what to do
in your current situation.
Speaking of the past means you assume
that people don't change their minds.
You're assuming people don't change when
they do. Then you think changing is bad.
Thus you cannot find a solution.
Your spouse promised you many things
at the point of marrying you.
That was based on how he felt at the time.
He felt that way at the time
when he wanted to marry you.
Once he is married, it's abnormal
to keep feeling the same way.
As he's already married, he has different
thoughts based on new circumstances.
You should be assessing
what to do under new circumstances.
It won't work if you approach it
by bringing up promises from the past.
It is perfectly normal to feel differently
before and after marriage.
I'm not saying you should become
a completely different person.
When children are young,
they are obedient.
Hence you remember how they were
and want them to be obedient
even when they are older.
Does a child stay the same when
he's a child, a teenager, and over 20?
He's a different person.
He's not the same.
And yet you think he is the same person.
You think, "He used to do as I say"
Who doesn't obey their parents
when they are a child?
1 out of 10 won't obey their parents
when they are young.
1 out of 10 will obey their parents
when they are grown up.
Do you understand?
Most will obey their parents
while they are young.
Most will disobey their parents
once they are grown up.
Why?
Because it's normal to do so.
A grown-up that always obeys
his parents is a slave, is he not?
He should live his own life.
A child has to obey his parent in order
to be cared for. He can't not obey.
If a child is hungry for praises
and love even after he is grown up,
you need to realize that
you didn't give him enough love
as a mother when he was young.
That's why I always say,"Give children
lots of love until they are 3 years old."
Don't feed them too much,
don't buy them too much clothes.
They only feed on
mother's love at that age.
If your child grew up to become
defiant and rebellious,
it's likely that
you've interfered too much.
You didn't allow them to live their lives
and were overbearing, hence the problem.
Children who were obedient at a young age
usually rebel once they are older.
9 out of 10 will.
Why is that?
Being obedient doesn't mean
the child has no mind of his own.
He is being submissive to parents
because he has no power.
Rebellion inevitably follows submission.
We don't normally see revolts
in our society.
And yet the military which has
the strictest rules
experiences the most revolts.
It is because suppression
surely leads to rebellion.
The stricter the parents are, the more
rebellious the children may become.
If you raised your child
with corporal punishment,
he may use physical violence against you
once he becomes old enough.
It's not that he is a bad kid.
It's the human's natural tendency,
a human character.
You feel distressed because you don't
acknowledge these human tendencies.
That's why life is hard for you.
Let's assume a man pursues
a woman for 5 years.
She kicks him around,
and throws his flowers back at his face.
He promises to become her slave
and treat her like a queen.
They finally get married.
The very day after marriage,
he starts abusing her.
(Audience Laughter)
Why is that? He has to get even.
If the women played
hard to get before marriage,
she should treat her husband
as a king once they are married.
Only then will things work out smoothly.
And yet that's not what people do.
People have problems because
they go against principles.
Conflicts don't just arise for no reason.
You can handle anyone or anything
if you deal in accordance with
the principles and tendencies.
You won't get along with even
the nicest person if you go against it.
What do we call Buddha's teachings?
We call it a religion,
but his teaching go beyond religion.
We call it a Buddhist religion,
but it's actually Buddhist law.
What is law? It's a principle.
They are principles.
They are principles like
nature's principles, mind's principles.
If we know the principles, use them
and live in accordance to them,
we can live life naturally
as if water flows.
If we use our bodies and minds
in accordance to biological principles,
we can live a healthy for a long time.
If we don't, our body breaks down earlier on.
Except for accidents.
It's the same with cars, no?
If you drive a car according to basic
driving principles, it lasts a long time.
If you drive it at high speeds,
it will break down fast.
You know how cars are, don't you?
Let's say a car lasts 10, 20 years
if driven well.
If it's a company car used among
5 different people,
will it break down faster?
Or will a car driven
by a single person break down faster?
It will break down faster
when used among 5 people.
Of course it will break down
if used long enough,
but even under the same amount of use,
a car driven among many people
will break down faster.
It's because they don't treat it
according to its tendencies.
Even objects, machinery acts this way.
How would people be?
My books don't say anything special.
You wonder how a monk would know
how to raise children or know of marriage.
Then how do we know
the movements of stars, the moon?
How do we launch a rocket?
We do so by knowing the principles.
Although you are married,
you don't know the principles of a relationship
between people, between husband and wife.
You raise children,
and yet you don't know the principles.
You have employees, or you are
an employee working under a boss,
and yet you don't know
the basic principles of how people think.
Because of this,
we are here to solve such issues together.
It's better to discuss actual
scenarios than me doing all the talking.
It's better that talks are specific,
just as we do field trips nowadays.
So don't worry even if you have
a different religious background.
Ask me whatever you want to know.
Don't say you are happy with your husband
when you actually hate him deep inside.
Then it's a waste of time.
You'll end up confessing that you hate him
5 minutes into the conversation anyway.
Now please raise your hand
if you have a question.